Guide to the Squatters' Collective Oral Histories Project OH.068
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Squatters' Collective Oral Histories Project
2008-2012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sorgen, Jeremy
Starecheski, Amy
OH.068
1 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes containing 19 access and master CDs and 1 hard drive containing 167 files of audio recordings, images, and transcripts in 25.86 GB.
19 sound discs (cd)
25.86 Gigabytes
The Tamiment Library first initiated the Squatters' Collective Oral Histories Project in 2008 as a larger effort to document the squatters' movement in New York City. The project was later continued by Amy Starecheski who conducted an additional thirty-seven interviews for her scholarly research in cultural anthropology. This collection is comprised of forty-four interviews documenting the experiences of individuals living as squatters in New York City between the 1980s and the 2000s. Interviews included in this project touch on a number of topics including general discussions about the experience and politics of squatting; legalization of squats and negotiations with the Urban Homesteading Assistance Board (UHAB); gentrification; and the experiences of women and minorities in squats. The majority of squatters interviewed in this collection lived in Manhattan's Lower East Side, but the collection also contains discussion of squats in the Mott Haven neighborhood of the South Bronx.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Tamiment Library first began conducting interviews for this collection in 2008. Interviews completed by Jeremy Sorgen on behalf of the library in 2008 were established as the Squatters' Collective Oral Histories Project, OH 068. In 2014, Amy Starecheski donated additional interviews interviews, which were incorporated into this collection. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.140.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into two series, Series I: Interviews by Jeremy Sorgen and Series II: Interviews by Amy Starecheski, based on the phase in which the interviews were conducted for this oral history project. Series in the collection have been named after the primary interviewer who conducted interviews for each phase of the project.Files within series have not been arranged.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Squatters' Collective Oral History Project was initiated by Tamiment Library in 2008 as a larger effort to document the squatters' movement in New York City. In 2008 Jeremy Sorgen, and undergraduate student at New York University, conducted seven oral history interviews on behalf of the Tamiment Library. The project was later continued by Amy Starecheski who conducted an additional thirty-seven interviews as research for her Ph.D. dissertation in Cultural Anthropology at the City University of New York, which focused on squatting and the transformation of squats into limited equity, low-income co-ops.
The history of squatting in New York City can be traced back to the nineteenth century, but the movement documented by this oral history project began as an outgrowth of an economic and housing crisis in the 1970s. Reacting to a lack of affordable housing and displacement caused by urban renewal projects, a number of city residents sought alternative housing by occupying vacant buildings in the city. Squatters in New York City were a diverse group that included bohemian artists, activists, undocumented immigrants, and displaced locals, among others. Throughout the 1990s, building owners and city officials worked to evict many of the squats, and while many were torn down or reclaimed by the city, squatters staged a number of successful efforts which allowed them to remain in their buildings. By the end of the 1990s, a number of squatters who still retained control of their buildings approached the Urban Homesteading Assistance Board (UHAB), a non-profit organization dedicated to converting city-owned buildings into low-income cooperatives, in an attempt to establish legal ownership of their homes. Over the years that followed, squatters in the Lower East Side began negotiations with UHAB and eventually reached a deal in 2002, which allowed UHAB to acquire eleven buildings that would eventually be sold back to residents once they were renovated and brought up to code. Many of the squats struggled to complete renovations to their buildings, however, and as of 2013 only five of the eleven buildings completed the legalization process.
Related Archival Materials
Squatters' Rights Collection: Fly Papers (TAM 363)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Jane Churchman Papers (TAM 313)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Jerry "The Peddler" Wade (TAM 366)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Kurt Reynertson Papers (TAM 335)
Squatters' Rights Collection: On Davis Papers (TAM 365)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Peter Spagnuolo Papers (TAM 336)
Squatters' Rights Collection: Roland Politi Papers (TAM 364)
Scope and Content Note
This collection is comprised of interviews of 37 individuals documenting their experiences living as squatters in New York City between the 1970s and the 2000s. The majority of squatters interviewed in this collection lived in Manhattan's Lower East Side, but the collection also contains discussion of squats in the Mott Haven neighborhood of the South Bronx. Individuals interviewed for this project come from diverse backgrounds and speak to the multitude of experiences among squatters.
Interviews in this collection address the general experience of life as a squatter in New York, and a large portion focus specifically on the process of transforming squats into legal, limited equity, low-income co-ops. In their discussions about legalization, interviewees recount their negotiations with the Urban Homesteading Assistance Board (UHAB), gentrification, reasons for seeking legalization, and their general opinions about the process. A number of interviews in this collection also touch on squatters' experiences, discussing the politics, organization, and social structure of squats. Several interviews also highlight the experiences of women and minorities living in squats, addressing issues including discrimination, underrepresentation, and child rearing. Additionally, the collection contains a number of interviews with housing rights activists who assisted squatters in their attempts to gain ownership of their buildings.
Oral history interviews in Series I: Interviews by Jeremy Sorgen were recorded as audio files, which were transferred to Access and Master CDs. Files from Series II: Interviews by Amy Starecheski were recorded as digital audio files and also consist of transcripts and JPEG images of the interviewees.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access CDs for audiovisual materials in the collection are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only.
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Oral histories (literary works); Squatters -- New York (State) -- New York; Housing, Cooperative |z New York (State) |z New York.; Tompkins Square Park Riot, New York, N.Y., 1988.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Social conditions.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Interviews by Jeremy Sorgen, 2008; 17 sound discs (cd); 2.09 Gigabytes in 13 files.
  Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
  Access CDs for audiovisual materials in the collection are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only.
  Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
  - Jerry the Peddler: Oral History Interview by Jeremy Sorgen, 2008-03-13-2012-04-26; cuid34444; 4 sound discs (cd); 848.6 Megabytes in 6 computer files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_16)
    Scope and Content Note
    In this interview Gerald Wade, aka Jerry the Peddler describes the earliest roots of organized squatting on the Lower East Side. He describes the Yippie squatting actions of the late 1970s and the Pope of Pot, a squatter, drug dealer, and cult leader. He discusses the importance of food, beer, and pot as organizing tools. Wade also describes the development and defense of La Plaza Cultural, where in 1986 they fed up to 500 people a day; some of those people opened Serenity House. He discusses the mounting tensions over Tompkins Square Park in the late 1980s, the riots, and ongoing protests, with which he was centrally involved. He also talks about the 1988 fire at 319 8th Street, and subsequent eviction and demolition of the building. The first session of the interview ends suddenly with a discussion of the May Day and Pot Parade actions in 1990. In the second session, Wade discusses the Triad, Tia Scott, his struggles with drug and alcohol addiction in the 1990s, the defense of the ABC Community Center, the 13th Street eviction, the eviction of Dos Blocos, and anarchist/communist dynamics in anti-war activism during the Persian Gulf War. He discusses the archives at Tamiment, his own archives, and the importance of history. He talks about how he got sober. Wade talks about the pig roasts he used to organize for May Day. He also discusses the legalization process, his experiences of becoming a homeowner, and the potential for squatting today.
    Biographical/Historical note
    Gerald Wade, aka Jerry the Peddler, grew up in west Texas. He was raised by his father and grandparents, and left home at age 15, which he notes as common experience among people in the squats. At 17 he joined the army. Having been a teenager in the 1960s, he acquired an "us against them" attitude, and during his time in the army became involved in Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) and anti-war activism, even while living on a base in California. When he was supposed to go to Vietnam, Wade went AWOL and lived in the hills in Big Sur for a month. He spent time in Los Angeles and then moved to Fort Worth, Texas where he was involved with draft counseling and the White Panthers. After getting arrested for being AWOL several times he went to Washington, DC for the 1971 May Day protests, where he was detained in RFK Stadium with 20,000 other protesters. He stayed in DC and got involved with the Yippies, who he cites as an important influence on the squatting scene. Between 1974 and 1980 started a relationship, had begun working steadily, and withdrew from politics. After his relationship ended in 1980, however, Wade moved to New York where he once again became involved in political activism. In New York he became connected with people in The Triad, squatted buildings on 7th Street by Avenue D, organized by Everything for Everybody, and after spending some time living in Tompkins Square Park settled in a squatted building on 9th Street. Wade also helped to organize Rock Against Regan, a touring concert, and when the group returned to NYC in 1984, and Wade and others from the group opened the building at 319 East 8th Street. After that point a number of buildings opened up along 8th Street.
  - Steven Englander: Oral History Interview by Jeremy Sorgen, 2008-04-06; cuid34445; 2 sound discs (cd); 379 kilobytes in 3 computer files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_32)
    In this interview Steven Englander discusses the 1980 founding of ABC No Rio and its surrogate parent organization Collaborative Projects (Colab). He discusses ABC No Rio's changing relationships with squatting and politics, describing the process by which No Rio became a social and practical hub of the squatting scene in the mid-1990s and how squatters played a central role in direct action campaigns to protect No Rio.
    He describes the decision-making process leading up to the plan to rebuild ABC No Rio rather than renovate. He also discusses the shifting dynamics of ABC No Rio and the local community, noting that few people who currently participate at No Rio actually live on the Lower East Side. In 1999 Englander moved into Umbrella House, a squat on Avenue C, and discusses the organization of that building. He also talks about characters from the scene, and why he would not characterize it as a movement, arguing that it did not go beyond squatting as a practice, or extend beyond the neighborhood and did not question private property.
    Steven Englander grew up in Wisconsin, the child of a pediatrician and a nurse. He attended private school and was raised in a comfortable, liberal environment with an emphasis on social justice. Drawn to the city's mythos, in 1980 he moved to New York City to attend New York University's film school. After becoming interested in Situationist critiques of media and Marxist economic theory in the mid-1980s, Englander got involved in the anarchist scene and later squatting. While working part-time as a production assistant and taxi driver, he wrote zines, fiction, and non-fiction about urbanism and political events. He was involved with the Black Eye zine, the Anarchist Switchboard, and ABC No Rio. In 1990 he became the assistant director of ABC No Rio. He later moved into No Rio as a squatter in 1994, with others, to defend the space against possible self-help eviction by the city. In 1997, he and all other residents at No Rio willingly vacated as part of a deal with the city to preserve No Rio as a community space, including a print shop, darkroom, computer room, and zine library. After almost a decade of raising money for renovations, in 2006 ABC No Rio acquired title to the building and began planning to rebuild.
  - Mac McGil: Oral History Interview by Jeremy Sorgen, 2008-04-04; 2 sound discs (cd) (Box Shared Tamiment 038)
  - Steve Harrington: Oral History Interview by Jeremy Sorgen, 2008-03-12; 4 sound discs (cd)
  - Carla Cubit: Oral History Interview by Jeremy Sorgen, 2008-04-26; cuid34446; 2 sound discs (cd); 1.27 Gigabytes in 4 computer files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_04)
    In this interview Carla Cubit talks briefly about her early life and describes her feelings of alienation from her family and friends. Later, she describes squatter politics and art, including squatter May Day, and John the Communist. She recalls dumpster diving to get food for the 13th Street community kitchen and being bullied by Butch, who terrorized the neighborhood. Cubit argues that the buildings with more people of color in them were evicted over time, while the majority white buildings were allowed to become co-ops; with gentrification squatted buildings have been literally and metaphorically white-washed. In the interview she mentions that when she sees people from that era on the streets she feels they avoid her. Cubit noticed that squatters were mostly white and middle class, and there were few black people, fewer black women and wondered if she was a token. She describes the cliquishness of the buildings on 13th Street, factionalization in the squatter community and tensions with other neighborhood residents, yet she still remembers it as a utopia of creativity, independence, and community. She recalls using piss buckets, stealing cable, and heating with wood stoves.
    Carla Cubit grew up in Kansas City, Missouri, where she was raised by her mother. She moved around frequently during childhood, and her mother struggled with alcohol and crack addiction. As a result Cubit often lived with her aunts. When she was 18, her boyfriend was killed, and Cubit left Missouri for New York City, hoping to get into theater. She had no place to stay, and ended up in shelters, where she was diagnosed as schizophrenic. She attended Borough of Manhattan Community College, studying liberal arts and became aware of alternative lifestyles, politics, and squatting. She also got involved with Unforgotten Voices, a homeless arts group, Hobo Theater, anti-psychiatry groups, and participated in a homeless encampment in City Hall Park. Cubit did some work days at a squat on 13th Street and then was invited to live there. After moving into 13th Street Cubit began selling art through American Primitive Gallery, as an "outsider artist," and performing spoken word and theater. Since 13th Street was evicted, she stopped squatting, and her art stopped selling. At the time of the interview Cubit lived in the projects and was a self-described "internet addict."
  - Art Cabrera: Oral History Interview by Jeremy Sorgen, 2008-05-21; 3 sound discs (cd)
- Series II: Interviews by Amy Starecheski, 2009-2012; 23.77 Gigabytes in 154 files.; 2 sound discs (cd)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  - Frank Morales: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2009-07-19; 2012-02-17; cuid34430; 2 sound discs (cd); 1.58 Gigabytes in 6 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_11)
    In the first session, Frank Morales discusses his upbringing on the Lower East Side, his experiences in the 1960s liberation theology and decision to go to seminary, and his early experiences with squatting while working as a priest in the Mott Haven neighborhood of the South Bronx. He describes the theory of spatial deconcentration and frames the abandonment of the 1970s as an attack on people of color and squatting as resistance to it. Later he discusses returning to the Lower East Side and squatting in that neighborhood, including losing several buildings to arson. He compares squatting in the Bronx and on the Lower East Side. In the second session, Morales primarily discussed his ideology regarding the value of property and the right to housing. Although not originally involved in the decision to move forward with UHAB and the legalization process, Morales shared his thoughts and feelings about the decision and noted his support for having UHAB as an ally versus antagonistic forces. He also discusses the difficulties of funding the legalization process and the "normalization" of squatting.
    Frank Morales was born in 1949 and grew up in Jacob Riis housing project on New York's Lower East Side. His father was Puerto Rican and his mother was Peruvian. Although raised Catholic, Frank became interested in Christianity through contact with a chaplain over his conscientious objector status. In 1973 he became an ordained Episcopal minister. Frank spent time in the South Bronx in the late 1970s and in 1985 he returned to the Lower East Side where he was an active squatter and political leader.
  - Alfa Diallo: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-07-30; cuid34431; 481.27 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_1)
    Alfa Diallo's interviews discusses his experience living at 544 East 13th Street. He describes opening the building, allocating spaces, and doing renovations. In this interview, Diallo also discusses the split that occurred among residents in his building.
    Alfa Diallo was born in Dakar, Senegal. He went to college in Senegal, then the Sorbonne in Paris, and moved to New York City in the early 1980s. Hanging out on the Lower East Side, he became friends with Rolando Politi, and was introduced to the squatters of East 13th Street. 539 East 13th, the first building opened was full, so he joined a group of people opening a new building across the street at 544 East 13th Street. Diallo worked in construction, and later began selling t-shirts at a flea market and doing administrative work at Cooper Union.
  - Bill Cashman: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-08-02; cuid34432; 1.5 Gigabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_2)
    In this interview Bill Cashman talks about how he came to squatting through his involvement in the punk scene and discusses the thrill of exploring abandoned buildings in Asbury Park, and a similar feeling on the Lower East Side. Cashman, who ended up living in C-Squat, describes the building's decision to phase out having people live in the basement as they were trying to legalize, and the legalization process overall. He talks about how spaces were allocated and contested in the building. Cashman also describes the conflict between the NYPD, Leftover Crack in 2003, and the increasing challenges of putting on shows in Tompkins Square Park. He describes working on his room and becoming a member of the house. Cashman was deeply involved in the process of finding a tenant, the Museum of Reclaimed Urban Spaces, for the C-Squat storefront, and he talks about that. Cashman also talks about his interest in history and his research into his building's past.
    Bill Cashman was born in New Jersey in 1982 and was raised by his mother, a nurse, and his grandmother. He was involved in the New Jersey punk scene in Asbury Park and New Brunswick, and started coming to Lower East Side squats for punk shows. He got involved with the band Choking Victim through organizing shows, and came to C-Squat originally as a band member's roommate.
    Access Restrictions
    The digital access copy of this interview is available by appointment in the Special Collections Reading Room. Email special.collections@nyu.edu to make an appointment.
  - Brett Pants: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-03-17; cuid34433; 217.75 Megabytes in 6 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_3)
    In this brief interview, Brett Pants talks about how he found himself at C-Squat and how he began squatting at a very early age, starting when he was still attending high school. Pants discusses the manual labor that he and his fellow squatters put into rebuilding C-Squat, as well as the emotional investment that he made in regards to the building and the residents of C-Squat, who he considers family. Pants admits that he never really believed that the legalization process would take place, and at the time of the interview felt very disillusioned and frustrated with what he perceived as UHAB's lack of progress in the whole process.
    Brett Lebowitz was born in 1973 and grew up in Canarsie, Brooklyn. When he was young he traveled and squatted in various places, but always ended up coming back to New York City. He started living in C-Squat by watching a friend's space, and when he was 19 he eventually got a space of his own in the building.
  - Dan Yafet: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-07-29; cuid34434; 478.15 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_5)
    In this interview, Dan Yafet talks about work days and decisions within the 209 East 7th Street building where he lived. He describes the make-up of the building's residents at that time, and later talks about the decision to cooperate with UHAB. Yafet also discusses his work with architect Paul Castrucci in helping to get the squatted buildings up to code. He continues to discuss the legalization process and financial issues that the squats faced with UHAB.